Guide to the C. J. Bulliet papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
C. J. Bulliet Papers,
1899-1952.
Bulliet, C. J. (Clarence Joseph), 1885-1951.
10 linear ft. (19 boxes: 16 document boxes; 1 custom-made box; 1 oversize box; 1 file card box; 1 mapcase shelf).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#0165
4079653
These papers contain the correspondence, photographs, press releases, programs and manuscripts of Clarence Joseph Bulliet (1883-1952) who was a prominent art and dramatic critic for the Indianapolis Star, Louisville Herald and Chicago Evening Press. The bulk of this collection is comprised of materials from the 1910s and early 1920s, when Bulliet was business manager for the touring company of Shakespearean actor Robert Bruce Mantell. Production photographs, press releases, production diaries and notes and drafts for Robert Mantell’s Romance, the biography of Mantell written by Bulliet, are included in this collection. This collection also contains photographs and souvenir programs from other productions; drafts of Bulliet’s literary works; printed materials and correspondence with Edward Albee, Julian Eltinge, Genevieve Hamper, Robert B. Mantell and Vera Zorina.
Biographical Note
Though best known as the influential art critic for The Chicago Daily News, Clarence Joseph (C.J.) Bulliet began as a drama critic and served as business manager for Robert Bruce Mantell's touring Shakespeare company between 1912 and 1923. Born in Corydon, Indiana in 1883, Bulliet changed his name from 'Bulleit' after World War I to escape any connection with Germany. After graduating from Indiana University in 1905, Bulliet embarked on a newspaper career, serving as a reporter for The Louisville Herald and The Indianapolis Star, where he worked from 1906-1911.
After reviewing Robert Bruce Mantell's production of Othello, Bulliet wrote the acclaimed Shakespearean star a letter, which sparked a connection that led to Bulliet's appointment as Mantell's business manager and biographer. As business manager between 1912 and 1923, Bulliet arranged the logistics and wrote press releases for Mantell's touring Shakespeare productions which traveled across the United States. When World War I halted the production, Bulliet worked as a press representative for D.W. Griffith's film The Birth of a Nation. Bulliet also worked on Mantell's biography throughout the tour, resulting in the publication of Robert Mantell's Romance in 1918, Bulliet's first published book.
Mantell was a celebrated Shakespearean actor who was especially known for his Lear and Richard III. Born in Scotland in 1854, Mantell veered towards the stage after a tumultuous adolescence and began his career as Francisco in Hamlet. Celebrated Shakespearean actress Madame Modjeska supported Mantell in New York, commenting that his Tybalt was "a stunner, and should not be killed". Mantell shot to fame in Fedora in 1883 and achieved acclaim for roles in Shakespeare and melodrama through the rest of the 19th century, before he became exiled from New York after an acrimonious alimony dispute. His return as Richard III to the Princess Theatre in 1904 was a triumph, with Mantell reputedly supported (according to his legend) by the ghosts of tragedian's past who cheered him from the audience.
After serving as Mantell's manager, Bulliet returned to journalism, writing for he Louisville Herald again from 1920 and moving to Chicago to write for The Chicago Evening Post in 1923, where he served as its editor and drama critic. When the Post was sold and became The Chicago Daily News in 1932, Bulliet was appointed its art critic. Art increasingly usurped Bulliet's interest in drama and Bulliet quickly became the most influential art critic in Chicago, supplementing his journalism with popular publications such as Apples and Madonnas: Emotional Expression in Modern Art (1927) and Paintings, an Introduction to Art (1934). Bulliet died in 1952.
Scope and Content
These records comprise correspondence, manuscript drafts, photographs, press releases, press clippings, printed materials and theatrical programs. Drafts of manuscripts and press releases include handwritten edits. Some photographs and souvenir programs are autographed or include an inscription. Printed materials include books by Clarence J. Bulliet and other authors.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in 5 series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1909-1951 and undated
Series II: Theatre Productions, 1909-1950
Subseries II.1: Robert Mantell, 1912-1920
Subseries II.2: Other Productions, 1909-1950
Series III: Writings, 1898-1935
Series IV: Subject Files, 1908-1948
Series V: Visual Materials, 1884-1946
Subseries V. 1: Catalogued Images, 1910-1937
Subseries V. 2: Non-Catalogued Materials, 1884-1946
Subseries V. 3: Catalogued Theatrical Images and Portraits, Undated
Subjects
Bulliet, C. J. (Clarence Joseph), 1883-1952.; Derby, George.; De Tréville, Yvonne, 1881-1954.; Horton, Edward Everett.; Klein, Charles, 1867-1915.; Mantell, Robert B. (Robert Bruce), 1854-1928.; Meyer, Annie Nathan, 1867-1951.; Moholy-Nagy, László, 1895-1946.; O'Hara, Maureen, 1920-; Skinner, Otis, 1858-1942.; Starr, Frances.; Walker, Stuart.; Zorina, Vera.; Theater.; Motion pictures.; Clippings.; Diaries.; Engravings.; Notebooks.; Poems.; Photographs.; Press releases.; Proofs.; Theater programs.; Dramatic critics.; Editors.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
1987 M-1987 Bulliet, Richard W. Gift
Gift of Richard W. Bulliet, 1982-1983, 1984, & 1987.
- Series I: Correspondence, 1909-1951 Undated
  Correspondence is divided into catalogued and non-catalogued materials, reflecting the previous arrangement of these materials. Mostly composed of Bulliet’s professional correspondence, this series includes letters, notes and telegrams and features correspondence from Edward Albee, John Barrymore, Hamilton Dobbin, Julian Eltinge, Genevieve Hamper, Robert B. Mantell and Vera Zorina. Non-catalogued material is arranged alphabetically by author. Catalogued images can be found in Series V, Visual Materials.
  - Catalogued
    - Albee, Edward, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Armes, William Dallam, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Barrymore, John, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Boucicault, Ruth, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Brady, Mr., Undated, circa 1910s (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bryan, William Jennings, Undated circa 1910s (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Bulliet, Katherine, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Cravens, John William, 1914-1916 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Derby, George, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Eltinge, Julian, 1911-1915 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Hamper, Charles, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Hamper, Genevieve, 1918-1928 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Henry, Alice, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Horton, Edward Everett, Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Klein, Charles, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Mantell, Robert Bruce, 1914-1928, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 16 to 17)
    - Meyer, Annie Nathan, Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Moholy-Nagy, Laszlo, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Nicholas, Anna, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - O’ Hara, Maureen, Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Price, Charles Wilson, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Skinner, Constance, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Skinner,Otis, Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Starr, Frances, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Treveille, Yvonne de, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Walker, Stuart, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Zorina, Vera, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Arranged
    - General, 1909-1923 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - A-B, 1909-1946 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - B, 1916-1930 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - C, 1913-1932 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - D, 1919-1929 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Dobbin, Hamilton, 1914-1930, (3 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 2 to 4)
    - E-G, Undated-1948 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - H-L, 1911-1948 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Leiber, Fritz, Undated-1919 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - M, 1911-1919 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Maxwell, John M., 1914-1921 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - N-R, 1910-1940 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - S-W, 1909-1951 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Series II: Theatre Productions, 1909-1950
  This series is divided into two subseries-- Robert Mantell’s theatre productions and productions by other artists.
  - Subseries II.1: Robert Mantell, 1912-1920
    Clarence J. Bulliet acted as the business manager for Robert Mantell’s Shakespearean tours across America between 1912 and 1923 and this subseries contains materials pertaining to the production, publicity and logistics of this operation. Much of this subseries is comprises press releases that announced the tour to each town. Following the original arrangement, these have been listed by performer or production, date or theatre. Short production diaries list the dates and locations of the tour and do not provide any commentary on the production or the tour. This subseries also contains press clippings, publicity fliers, programs and some correspondence.
    - General, 1913-1920 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Press Releases
      - Performer or Production, 1910s-1920s
        - Dickson, J.B (Box 3, Folder 4)
        - Hamlet (Box 3, Folder 5)
        - Hamper Genevieve (Box 3, Folder 6)
        - King Lear (Box 3, Folder 7)
        - Leiber, Fritz (Box 3, Folder 8)
        - Louis XI (Box 3, Folder 9)
        - Macbeth (Box 3, Folder 10)
        - Mantell, Robert, (2 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 11)
        - "Miscellaneous" (Box 3, Folder 12)
        - Richard III (Box 3, Folder 13)
        - Richelieu (Box 3, Folder 14)
        - Shakespeare (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Date
        - 1912 (Box 3, Folder 16)
        - 1913 (Box 3, Folder 17)
        - 1914 (Box 3, Folder 18)
        - 1916 (Box 3, Folder 19)
        - 1917 (Box 3, Folder 20)
        - 1920 (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Theatre, 1910s-1920s
        - Adelphi Theatre-- Philadelphia (Box 3, Folder 22)
        - American Theatre--St. Louis (Box 3, Folder 23)
        - Auditorium (Box 3, Folder 24)
        - Belasco--New York (Box 3, Folder 25)
        - Berchel Theater (Box 3, Folder 26)
        - Boston Opera House (Box 3, Folder 27)
        - Broad Street Theatre (Box 3, Folder 28)
        - Colonial Theatre (Box 3, Folder 29)
        - Cort Theatre--San Francisco (Box 3, Folder 30)
        - Empire Theatre (Box 3, Folder 31)
        - English’s Opera House--Indianapolis (Box 3, Folder 32)
        - Ford’s Opera House (Box 3, Folder 33)
        - Forty-Fourth Street Theatre--New York City (Box 3, Folder 34)
        - Grand Opera House--Cincinnati (Box 3, Folder 35)
        - Harmanus Bleecker Hall--Albany (Box 3, Folder 36)
        - Hartman Theatre (Box 3, Folder 37)
        - Hollis (Box 3, Folder 38)
        - Jefferson Theatre--St. Louis (Box 3, Folder 39)
        - Lexington Opera House (Box 3, Folder 40)
        - Lyceum Theatre--Rochester (Box 3, Folder 41)
        - Lyric Theatre--Memphis (Box 3, Folder 42)
        - Macaulay’s Theatre--Louisville (Box 3, Folder 43)
        - Majestic Theatre--Brooklyn (Box 3, Folder 44)
        - Mason Opera House--New York City (Box 3, Folder 45)
        - Montauk Theatre--Brooklyn (Box 3, Folder 46)
        - Murat Theatre--Indianapolis (Box 4, Folder 1)
        - New Colonial Theatre--Bluefield (Box 4, Folder 2)
        - New Jefferson Theatre--University of Virginia (Box 4, Folder 3)
        - New Lyric Theatre (Box 4, Folder 4)
        - Nixon Theatre--Pittsburgh (Box 4, Folder 5)
        - Olympic Theatre--Chicago (Box 4, Folder 6)
        - Parsons Theatre (Box 4, Folder 7)
        - Princess Theatre--Montreal (Box 4, Folder 8)
        - Providence Opera House (Box 4, Folder 9)
        - Shubert Theatre--Rochester (Box 4, Folder 10)
        - Shubert Majestic--Providence (Box 4, Folder 11)
        - Standard Theatre--New York City (Box 4, Folder 12)
        - Strand Theatre (Box 4, Folder 13)
        - Teck Theatre--Buffalo (Box 4, Folder 14)
        - Tulane Theatre (Box 4, Folder 15)
        - Vendome Theatre--Nashville (Box 4, Folder 16)
        - Wieting Opera House--Syracuse (Box 4, Folder 17)
        - Worcester Theatre (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, 1917-1920 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Programs, 1918-1919 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Publicity Fliers, Undated, 1910s-1920 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Press Clippings, 1910s-1920 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Production Diaries
      - 1912, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 1 to 2)
      - 1913, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 3 to 4)
      - 1914, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 5 to 6)
      - 1914-1915, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 7 to 8)
      - 1915 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - 1916-1917 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - 1917-1918 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - 1920 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Subseries II.2: Other Productions, 1909-1950
    This small subseries contains press clippings, publicity fliers, programs and special souvenir programs from productions that Bulliet attended, including The Blue Bird, Chantecler, Cyrano de Bergerac, Too Hot for Paris and The Vagabond King. This subseries also contains a souvenir program from D.W. Griffith’s film The Birth of a Nation, for which Bulliet served as a press representative.
    - General, 1909-1946 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Actors and Actresses--Press Releases and Clippings, 1909 Undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Publicity Fliers, 1909-1950 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Programs, 1918-1952 Undated, (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 26 to 27)
    - Souvenir Books
      - Benefit Actors’ Fund, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 28)
      - The Birth of a Nation, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 29)
      - The Blue Bird, Undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Chantecler, 1911 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Cyrano de Bergerac, Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Earl Carroll Vanities, Undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - The Eve of Saint Mark, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - The Grand Guignol Players, 1923 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Katherine Cornell, A Gallery of Stage Portraits, Undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - King Richard II, Undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Life with Father--includes Press Releases, Undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - The Press Agents Show, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Raquel Miller, Undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - La Saison Russe, 1911 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Theatre Guild, Undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - Too Hot for Paris, Undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - The Vagabond King, Undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - Whitford Kane, Undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Series III: Writings, 1898-1935
  Drafts of Bulliet’s press releases, articles, poetry, prose and non-fiction are included within this series. The main work represented here is Robert Mantell’s Romance, Bulliet’s biography of Mantell: this series contains notes, several drafts, press clippings, correspondence and an edition autographed by Mantell. Drafts of some of Bulliet’s other non-fiction and creative writings are also included and this series contains drafts of newspaper articles, poems, plays, short stories and literary notebooks, which served as creative scrapbooks for Bulliet.
  - Articles--with Notes, Undated-1922, (4 Folders) (Box 5, Folder 17 to 20)
  - Articles--Clippings, 1931-1932 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Articles--Clippings Book, 1909-1910 (Box 12)
  - Diary--Personal Appointments, 1908-1912 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Literary Notebooks, 1898-1935, (9 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 13 to 21)
  - Poems, Undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Plays, Undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Press Releases, 1911 Undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Prose, Undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Robert Mantell’s Romance
    - Partial Draft--with Notes, Undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence and Clippings, 1914-1915 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Notes, Undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Draft--Handwritten, Undated (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Draft--Handwritten, Undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Edition--Autographed by Robert Mantell, 1918 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Sonnets of the Stage, Undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Series IV: Subject Files, 1908-1948
  Bulliet’s original arrangement of these subject files is retained for this small series, which includes materials relating to Bulliet’s professional and personal life. Personal subject files are primarily clippings and financial documents. Professional subject files include press releases, correspondence and clippings from other projects that Bulliet worked on, including the The Black Stork, The Crisis and the American Negro Music Festival. A small number of printed books and programs that Bulliet kept are included within this series.
  - General, 1917-1948 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - American Negro Music Festival, 1944-1945 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - The Black Stork, 1917 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Books and Printed Materials (Box 11)
  - Banquet to Fred Block--Booklet--Friar’s Club--1929 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Don’t Do That: a book on etiquette--by William Collier, 1909 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Louis XI--by Henry Irving, Undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Tirana Diabala--by J. Lester Mee, 1946 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Bulliet Family, 1940 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Bulliet, CJ--Clippings about, 1926-1929 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - The Crisis, 1916-1917 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Financial Documents, 1910-1919 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Financial Documents, 1918-1919, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 22 to 23)
  - Hamper, Genevieve, 1929-1930 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Lanfang, Mei, Undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Mantell, Robert, Undated-1908 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Series V: Visual Materials, 1884-1946
  The majority of this series is composed of photographs of actors and production photographs from film and theatre, and a collection of theatrical portraits and subject files. Bulliet had an extensive collection of autographed portraits and much of this series has been cross-indexed in the Brander Matthews Dramatic Museum Portrait Collection. The series includes catalogued and non-catalogued materials, and retains the earlier arrangement.
  - Subseries V.1: Catalogued Images, 1910-1937
    Included here are previously catalogued portraits and original drawings.
    - Ayoe, Madame--Autographed, 1910 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Bell, Claire--Autographed, Undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Enters, Anga, 1937 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Hoffman, Gertrude--Autographed, Undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - King, Alexander, 1928 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Mantell, Robert--Autographed, 1910 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Meeker, Chris Marie, Undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Meeker, Chris Marie, Undated (Box 14-L-1)
    - Montana, Bull--Autographed, 1923 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Riedell, Boris, Undated (Box 14-L-1)
    - Sinnott Lillian--Autographed, Undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Snyder, Corydon--with Enclosed Letter, 1926-1927 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Sullivan, Margaret, 1936 (Box 14-L-1)
    - Wall, Bernhardt, 1926 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Weed, Raphael A, 1915-1918 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Subseries V.2: Non-Catalogued Materials, 1884-1946
    The non-catalogued materials include an array of portraits of artists and productions, extensive photographs of Robert Bruce Mantell in his Shakespearean roles and Gordon Craig’s design for Lady Macbeth’s chamber in Macbeth.
    - General, 1902-1946 Undated, (2 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 16 to 17)
    - General--Richard III--Mary Boland, Undated (Box 14-L-1)
    - Atlantic City Beauty Contest, 1922 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Craig, Gordon--Design for Macbeth-Illustration of Lady Macbeth's Chamber for 1.5--with Notes, Undated (Box 14-L-1)
    - Dobbins, H. H, 1923 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Edison, Robert--with wife, Undated (Box 14-L-1)
    - Eltinge, Julian, Undated (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Fashion--Henry Brothers Photographs, Undated (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Frohman, Charles--Stars of the 1909-1910 Season, 1909-1910 (Box 14-L-1)
    - Hamper, Genevieve, Undated (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Huara, Helba--with Personal Note, 1929 (Box 14-L-1)
    - Mantell, Robert--[as Hamlet], Undated (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Mantell, Robert--as King Lear, Undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Mantell, Robert, 1884-Undated, (3 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 1 to 3)
    - Mantel Family, Undated (Box 14-L-1)
    - Movie Scenes, Undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - News Service Photographs, 1922-1923 Undated, (2 Folders) (Box 10, Folder 5 to 6)
    - Performers, Undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Play Scenes, 1916-1917 Undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Police Department Photo, [1927] (Box 14-L-1)
    - Portraits--Autographed, Undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Portraits--Autographed, Undated (Box Flat File 273)
    - Raye, Faye, 1926 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Universal Pictures--Publicity Stills, Undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Subseries V.3: Catalogued Theatrical Images and Portraits, Undated
    The bulk of these materials comprise photographs of actors and productions. The materials in this subseries were catalogued previously and the original arrangement has been preserved.
    - Theatrical Images and Portraits--List of, Undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Abarbanell, Lina - Clifford, Kathleen, Undated (6 Folders) (Box 13, Folder 2 to 7)
    - Coghlan, Gertrude - Gunning, Louise, Undated (6 Folders) (Box 14, Folder 1 to 6)
    - Hackett, James K. - Lloyd, Alice, Undated (4 Folders) (Box 15, Folder 1 to 4)
    - Loftus, Cecelia - Owen, Margaret, Undated (5 Folders) (Box 16, Folder 1 to 5)
    - Parker, Louis-Napoleon - Sylva, Marguerita, Undated (5 Folders) (Box 17, Folder 1 to 5)
    - Taliaferro, Alice - Zangwell, Israel, Undated (4 Folders) (Box 18, Folder 1 to 4)
    - Actor's Church Alliance--Chicago Chapter - Scenes from Plays--"The Way to the Heart," Undated (4 Folders) (Box 19, Folder 1 to 4)